Hello my name is Andrew Van Slaars and this video is and introduction to RiotJS
a lightweight, react-like UI library that allows you to create your own custom tags
In this introductory video we will cover
how to get riot installed and up and running on your page
how to create and compile a custom tag
how to get data into your tag and how to use that data in expressions
and how to create a tag that allows user interaction through a basic form
now let's get our environment setup and get into the code
let's take a look at my initial setup
I'm using atom as my code editor but use whatever tool you are most comfortable with if you're going to follow along
I've created a root directory for the project and have atom pointed at that
I also have a terminal window open to that root directory and of course I'm running chrome
so we can see the results of our work
let's do a little bit of setup and then we can get into the code
You will need Node installed so we can install modules through NPM
If you don't already have that setup, you can do that on nodejs.org
by clicking the green install button
let's install some node modules with NPM
First we want to install the riot CLI by typing npm install dash g riot
this is going to give us the command line interface we need to compile our tags
we'll also be using a simple HTTP server to serve up our page
we can set that up by typing in
NPM install dash g HTTP hyphen server
and if you don't already have bower setup
you can add that by running npm install dash g bower
and now with bower installed we can add the riot js files to our project by running bower install riot
and you'll see that this has created a bower components directory in the project
now the riot js files are available for us to use
now that we have all of our files in place, let's take a quick look at the HTML file that we'll be starting with
as you can see, it's a basic HTML page
there's a heading one that's just static content
and I have a script tag that points to the riot.min.js file inside the bower components
and then there's an empty set of script tags the that we're going to use to add our own code
let's fire up the server we installed a moment ago
by typing in http dash server
and now that our server is running
let's load our page in a browser
and our page should load right up
now I'm just going to keep the web server running and open a new tab in the console
so we have that available to run our commands when we get to them
let's get started creating our first custom tag
the first thing we need to do is create a file to store our tag definition so I'm going to add that to the tags directory
and I'm going to name my tag hello dash world dot tag
we'll start by wrapping the definition in the tag we want to create
now that we have the shell for the tag in place, let's give it some content
and that's enough to give us a basic tag definition
riot tags are compiled into javascript
there is an option to include this compiler and allow the compilation step to happen in the browser
but for these examples
we're going to pre-compile our tags
for this we'll use the riot CLIwe installed earlier using NPM
we'll start by typing in the riot command
and then we'll tell riot what to compile
and we'll see that riot has taken our hello world dot tag file
and created a hello world dot js file in the same location
let's take a look at the result of that compilation
our javascript file contains a simple call to the tag method that riot provides
its first argument is the name of the tag, the second is a string that represents the template for our tag
and the third is a function that takes an options argument
now let's wire up our page to use our tag
back in index dot html
I need to add a script tag that points to hello world dot js
we also need to add our tag to the page
and finally we need to add a call to the mount method that riot provides to tell it to load the tag on the page
now that we have our tag defined
our script references are in place
and we've made a call to riot's mount method to tell it to load onto the page, let's take a look at it in the browser
and when we refresh the page in the browser, we should see our hello world content from our custom tag
so we've created a custom tag but it's only displaying static content so it's not very useful
let's look at how we can make our tag a little bit more interesting by passing it some data to display
let's say I want my tag to take a property called greet with a name to display as part of our message
it would look like this
now my tag has a greet attribute and I've passed it the value John
and what I'd like is for the output of the tag to say hello john instead of hello world
in order to use this value as part of the display we'll need to update our tag file to use an expression
in my hello world tag file I'm going to replace world with an expression
that calls opts dot greet
if you remember from earlier, opts is the name of the argument that's passed into the function
that we saw as the third argument in riot's tag method
now that we've added our expression
let's make sure all of our files are saved
and we can recompile our tag
we'll run the same riot command that we did before. passing it tags slash hello world dot tag
it'll replace our javascript file
and now when we look in the browser, we should see hello john
and as you can see, it's as easy as creating an attribute and adding an expression to pass a value into our custom tag
we can also pass data into our tags using riot's mount method
if we remove the greet attribute from our hello world tag
and then update our mount method
to pass in an object that has a greet property
we should see our tag render
with the message hello joe
and it works
note that we didn't do a recompile this time. Nothing in our tag definition changed
we just passed in the value a different way
now let's say we had a reason to put two of these tags on our page
I'm going to copy the hello world tag
paste a second one
save my file and refresh the browser
and we should see two hello joe messages printed out
when riot mounts the tag it's going to pass the data into each instance
if instead of passing data in the mount method we gave each instance of this tag its own attribute
we should see two different values
so let's check that out
I'll remove the value that I'm passing into moun
and then I'm going to give each tag a greet attribute
and again I'll refresh the browser
and you'll notice that each tag prints out the value that was passed to its specific greet attribute
now let's say we have a third instance of the hello world tag
but this time we're not going to give it an attribute value
when Ilook at that in the browser, my third instance just says hello and has no name
if I go back and pass an object to the mount method again
my tag that doesn't have an attribute will use this as the default value
you'll notice that my third tag says hello joe
it's pulling that value from the mount method
and the first two tags are using the attribute value
so passing this object into the mount method is a great way to set default values
and then you can override them with attributes on specific tags
showing data is helpful but if you're going to make anything interactive you'll need to accept input from users as well
let's create a new tag that incorporates a form
to stick with our super simple hello world theme
we'll create a tag with a single input that allows a user to type in the name portion of our greeting
let's create a new tag file
and we'll call it hello form dot tag
and the tag we're going to want to use will be hello dash form
inside our hello form tag we'll need a form which we can define with a standard HTML form
and we'll give our form a single input
and we'll give it a name
greet
and in order to submit our form we'll give it a button
and when we submit the form we want a message to be displayed with the name that was input
so let's add a message
we're going to need to use an expression to put our name in
now what we need to do is define the action for our form
because right now won't do anything
and we need to setup our mapping from our hello input to the this dot greeting variable that we put in our expression
to do this I'm going to add a set of script tags at the bottom of my tag
and inside the script tags I'm going to define a function that will act as my form's event handler
inside this function I'm going to take the greet input value and assign it to this dot greeting
and now I need to attach this function to the form as its submit handler
now that our tag is setup we're going to need to compile it so we can add it to our page
since we now have multiple tag files
let's look at a way to use the compiler to compile all of our tags into a single javascript file
when we run the riot command to compile a tag our first argument is the source
we can pass just a directory name
and riot will find all of the tag files in that directory and compile them all to javascript
so let's run the riot command and point it to the tags directory
Iwant to make the second argument the name of my output javascript file so that all of my tags end up in a single output
and when I run this, it'll take all of the tags in the tags directory, compile them into javascript
and the output will be in all dot js
and you'll see it has created our new file
we can take a look at that
and you'll notice that the hello form tag definition has our say hello function defined inside of it
now that we have our tags all defined in a single javascript file
let's update index dot html to point to our new javascript output
now that we've updated that we're also going to need to reference our new tag on the page
and we'll need to tell riot to mount our new tag
and now that we've done that let's taek a look in the browser and see our new output
and you'll see that we now have a single input our button that says hello
and the start of a hello message
Ican put a value in the form
and when I submit the form it'll update my output message
you'll notice that even though it took my value from the form and put it into my output
it still left that value in the input
let's go clean that up
back in my tag definition
I'm going to update my function
to clear out this dot greet
and I'll save that
now that I've made an update I'm going to need to recompile my tags
so this time let's tell riot to just watch the tags directory
and every time it sees a change I'm going to have it recompile the javascript
we do that by running the same command we used last time and this time we'll pass it the w switch for watch
it'll recompile the tags and you'll notice that it now says that it's watching
for all the files with a tag extension in the tags directory
and with our tag recompiled with our new change let's go to the browser and take a look
and that didn't work let's take a look at why
okay the reason that didn't work is I assigned the empty string to greet instead of greet dot value
so let's update that
save it
you'll see that our watch recompiles our javascript
Ican refresh the browser
type in a name
and now it updates my message
and clears out the form field
alright when we look at this new tag we created
you might notice that my output is essentially doing the same thing that my original hello world tag does
the nice thing about riot is that it allows us to compose our application by nesting tags
so I'm going to replace this h three with my greeting
and pass it an instance of my hello world tag
when I save that the watch shoudl recompile it
and when Igo back to the browser and refresh
I can go in here and I can pass it a new name
and it still works
but the nice thing about this is if I decide I want to change my hello world tag
say we make that a little smaller by changing it to an h five
I save it
the watch recompiles
and when I refresh, it'll be updated everywhere I reference hello world including inside of the hello form tag
everythign still works
and now that hello world tag allows me to make changes in one place and they get cascaded through wherever it's used
alright let's make one more change to our hello form tag
I'm going to go in here
and I really don't my hello world tag to be displayed when all it says is hello
so I'd like to hide this until the this dot greeting value is populated
riot gives us a built in attribute called show
we can pass that an expression
this expression will look at this dot greeting and if it's a falsey value so undefined or null
then show will hide our element
and if it's a truthy value, meaning it's populate
hello world will display the message
so let's take a look at that
I can refresh the browser
and you'll see that hello is no longer displayed
so if I put a name in here
and submit my form
it'll populate this dot greeting
and display the hello world tag
one of riot's strengths is brevity
it has a very small API a small file size and it allows us to write succinct code
so let's go look at our tag one more time and clean it up a little bit
my say hello function that I'm using as an event handler can be shortened
by removing the function
and the call to this
and Ican save this
it'll be recompiled
when I refresh my browser I'll see that it doesn't work
because I forgot the parenthesis
so I can shorten my function to say hello with opening and closing parenthesis
my tags will load
and my form will still work
the other thing I can do with riot
is leave out the script tags
when I recompile that and go back to my browser and refresh
notice my hello world tags still show up and Ican type a name in here
and my form still works
if we look at our compiled javascript
even though I left out the this and the keyword function
riots compilation step put it back in for me
Ilike to put the script tags in
I do like the abbreviated function definition syntax though so I'll keep that in there
we didn't do anythign too crazy
but this is a good starting point
if you were looking for something more advanced Ido plan on creating more videos like this
and to continue adding to the complexity as the videos progress
thanks for watching and if you have any feedback or suggestions I'd love to hear what you have to say